<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Gustavo Pinto - Articles</title>
		<description>Web log by Gustavo Pinto</description>
		<link>http://gustavopinto.org</link>
		<atom:link href="http://gustavopinto.org/feed.articles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			
			<item>
				<title>The story behind casual contributors</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of the paper &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.github.io/lost+found/saner2016.pdf&quot;&gt;More Common Than You Think: An In-Depth Study of Casual Contributors&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. For the impatient, there is a summary of the summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casual contributors are rather common&lt;/strong&gt;. 48.98% of the overall contributors that we analyzed are actually casual contributors. However, these contributors are responsible for only 1.73% of the total contributions in our set of analyzed projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casual contributions are far from being trivial&lt;/strong&gt;. After a manual inspection of a sample of casual contributions, we found that although 28.64% of them are related to grammar and typo fixes, 30.20% of them fix bugs, 18.75% propose new features, and 8.85% refactor code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casual contributions are well liked&lt;/strong&gt;. These contributions are perceived as a beneficial phenomenon from the perspective of project maintainters and casual contributors. Personal needs was the most reported motivation for the casual contributors. As a shortcoming, project maintainters reported an increasing number of reviews, which demands time from core developers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github changed the way developers contribute to OSS projects, in particular by providing a single process of contribution, which is called pull-based model. Using this model, developers do not need to have write access to the repository in order to provide changes to the software. This kind of environment, together with its contribution model, encourages newcomers to participate in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while some contributors want to have a key role on the project, some others do not share the same desire, although they still want to contribute nevertheless. In fact, it is well-known that popular projects have a restricted set of core developers, who drive the project, but also a broad set of &amp;quot;not that involved&amp;quot; developers, which are responsible for a long tail of small contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the growing number of newcomers interested in contributing to OSS, little is known about this particular kind of contributor: the &lt;em&gt;casual contributor&lt;/em&gt;. In a study published on &lt;a href=&quot;http://saner.inf.usi.ch/&quot;&gt;SANER&amp;#39;16&lt;/a&gt;, we investigate (1) how common casual contribtuors are, (2) what are the characteristics of their contributions, and (3) how they are perceived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in this blog post, we will describe the main findings of the paper. If you want to know more about this research, consider reading the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.github.io/lost+found/saner2016.pdf&quot;&gt;pre-print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;oss-selection&quot;&gt;OSS selection&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We selected the top 20 most popular open-source projects hosted on Github written in: C, C++, Clojure, CoffeeScript, Erlang, Go, Haskell, Java, JavaScript, Objective-C, Perl, PHP, Python, Ruby, Scala, and TypeScript. Our initial corpus comprises 320 mature, non-trivial, OSS projects. However, we removed 45 false-positive projects (&lt;em&gt;e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; projects that are not software projects). Our final list of projects included &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails&quot;&gt;rails&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/django/django&quot;&gt;django&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/torvalds/linux/&quot;&gt;linux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;surveys-with-practitioners&quot;&gt;Surveys with practitioners&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conducted two surveys with 197 the casual contributors and 64 project maintainers. These surveys were aimed at understanding the motivation, the benefits, and the drawbacks of this kind of contribution. Given the opportunity, I would like to thank the 261 developers that answered the survey. Assuming that it took about 10 minutes to answer the survey, the combined effort amounts to 2 full days. As one reviewer said, &amp;quot;The big deal is the story in the survey part&amp;quot;. &lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observed that 65.8% of our respondents contribute to OSS at least once per month, and 75.2% of them are used to making casual contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-common-are-casual-contributors-in-oss-projects?&quot;&gt;How common are casual contributors in OSS projects?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure below presents an overall picture of some of the studied projects. Each histogram groups the projects analyzed of each programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-casual/overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Contributions per programming language&quot; height=&quot;330&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some extent, the analyzed projects have a similar characteristic: most of the contributors perform very few contributions. A non-negligible number of contributors (48.98%) performed a single contribution, which varies from programming language to programming language (&lt;em&gt;e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; C projects have 39% of casual contributors, whereas JavaScript has 61%). Based on this finding, we decided that the casual contributor is a contributor that performed at most one commit to a software project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This significant number of casual contributors might lead one to believe that an important proportion of the projects are intrinsically made by casual contributions. In reality, we found the opposite: these casual contributors are responsible for only 1.73% of the total number of contributions in our corpus of OSS projects (linux: 1.02%, rails: 3.46%, django: 3.19%). For a more detailed perspective, next figure shows the percentage of the casual contributors (top) and contributions (bottom) for each programming language analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-casual/percentage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Percentage of casual contributors&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;330&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that the programming language used matters. With some exception, projects written in static typed programming languages (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, C, TypeScript and C++) seem to be less favorable to receive casual contributions than those using dynamic typed ones (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, Ruby, Python and JavaScript). We believe this is because scripting programming languages are more concise than procedural and object-oriented ones, and size really matters when it comes to casual contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-the-characteristics-of-a-casual-contribution?&quot;&gt;What are the characteristics of a casual contribution?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observed that the number of additions, deletions and files touched of contributions do not vary signifi- cantly among the analyzed projects. In particular, the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thoughtbot/paperclip/&quot;&gt;paperclip&lt;/a&gt; is the one with the highest number of additions and deletions among the Ruby projects. See table below. With more than 8 years old, 63% of its contributors are casual ones, who contributed to 12.74% of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Change&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3rd Quartile&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Std. Dev&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Additions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deletions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also analyzed the contributions with the lowest number of additions and deletions. In fact, 22.7% of the casual contributions performed on Ruby projects changed a single line of code. Some of them include, (1) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thoughtbot/paperclip/commit/6f2ca93&quot;&gt;preventing a type from being null&lt;/a&gt;, (2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thoughtbot/paperclip/commit/d49bca2&quot;&gt;updating documentation files&lt;/a&gt;, or (3) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thoughtbot/paperclip/commit/62a9f64&quot;&gt;setting an option to a default value&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also analyzed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_significance&quot;&gt;statistically significant&lt;/a&gt; sample of 384 casual contributions. We identified 8 categories of casual contributions, summarized next. Afterwards, we discuss the top 3 ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;%&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bug Fix&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;116&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;30.20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;28.64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add new feature&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.75%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Refactoring&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;8.85%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Update dependencies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;6.51%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Improve error message&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;3.64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Improve resource usage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;2.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add test cases&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;1.30%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bug fix&lt;/strong&gt;. It is the most common kind of casual contribution found in our dataset. Some examples include: (1) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TransitApp/SVProgressHUD/commit/eebd6ec&quot;&gt;layout fix&lt;/a&gt;, (2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/koalaman/shellcheck/commit/f054e2e&quot;&gt;fixing compilation problems&lt;/a&gt;, and (3) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lulzlabs/AirChat/commit/03cd91d&quot;&gt;fixing a broken URL&lt;/a&gt;. Still, some bug fixes are far from being trivial, as the one that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/torvalds/linux/commit/ddca3b8&quot;&gt;fixed a race condition at the linux operating system&lt;/a&gt;. Not only difficult to identify (such bugs are non-deterministic), the solution employed was also scattered between C preprocessors, which difficulties the reasoning of the compiled program.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;. This category includes fix for typos, grammar, translation, formatting, and documentation issues. Although these contributions do not require significant programming effort, we found contributions that have &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/codecombat/codecombat/commit/237b97a&quot;&gt;thoroughly rewritten the original material&lt;/a&gt;. Also, we found that 27 out of these 110 contributions were fixing typos on code examples. This finding reinforces the importance of complete and verified working code examples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add New Feature&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of the examples include (1) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rg3/youtube-dl/commit/1a2adf3&quot;&gt;adding a new option for a command line tool&lt;/a&gt;, (2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/angular/angular.js/commit/da9eac8&quot;&gt;adding support for disabling an option&lt;/a&gt;, and (3) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apenwarr/sshuttle/commit/95c9b78&quot;&gt;adding support for IPv6 remote hosts&lt;/a&gt;. Interestingly, 24 out of the 72 contributions in this category were performed at the Linux operating system. Most of them were adding support for a new driver/device, which usually require few additions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-casual-contributors-and-project-maintainers-perceive-casual-contributions?&quot;&gt;How do casual contributors and project maintainers perceive casual contributions?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explicitly asked casual contributors and project maintainers &amp;quot;what motivates casual contributors&amp;#39; behavior&amp;quot;, and the top cited perceived motivation was &lt;strong&gt;scratch their own itch&lt;/strong&gt;, highly mentioned by both casual contributors (90 out of 197) and project maintainers (23 out of 64). Part of this high number of casual contributions can be explained by the pull-request model, which provided a clear and easy contribution process. It was mentioned by 9 out of 64 project maintainters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aligned with some studies on the motivation behind OSS contributors, we found that &lt;strong&gt;give back to community&lt;/strong&gt; fosters casual contributions, as said by one casual contributor &amp;quot;As I use a lot of OSS projects, I like to give back to the community&amp;quot;. Another motivation that is inline with the literature is &lt;strong&gt;gaining reputation and prestige&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not among the top cited motivations, we found that four casual contributors reported that their motivation was &lt;strong&gt;improving the project&lt;/strong&gt;. The following quotes clearly illustrate such motivation: &amp;quot;I want to improve the quality of the project&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;That the project is in better shape after my contribution&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to motivation, we investigated the reasons why casual contributors do not become full active contributors. &lt;strong&gt;Lack of time&lt;/strong&gt; was far the most cited reason by the casual contributors (96 out of 197), like one mentioned &amp;quot;I don’t have time to devote to a more active role&amp;quot;.  From the perspective of the project maintainters, &lt;strong&gt;Lack of time&lt;/strong&gt; was also the most mentioned reason why casual contributors do not become a long term contributor (17 out of 64 respondents). The following quote exemplify it: &amp;quot;People often don’t have the time or desire to be long term contributors&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found people who reported that they do not contribute because of their &lt;strong&gt;limited skills or knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Some also mentioned that the effort and knowledge needed to become a full contributor was too high. In both cases, they prefer to work on small or peripheral issues, which do not need specific abilities and usually require low effort. Like one of them said: &amp;quot;lack of skills (most of the low hanging fruit is gone)&amp;quot;. Project maintainers noticed this, and eight participants mentioned that &lt;strong&gt;code/project is hard to learn&lt;/strong&gt; was a reason why casual contributors do not become more active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also asked the participants their opinion about the main benefits and problems brought by the casual contributors phenomenon. The overall impression is that the benefits overcome the drawbacks brought by this phenomenon. One quote from a project maintainter shows: &amp;quot;Every little piece helps everyone else. We stand on the shoulders of many small giants. Problems? None&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, the most reported problems were &lt;strong&gt;Time spent by the core members to review newcomers’ code&lt;/strong&gt; (reported by 12 people) and &lt;strong&gt;contributions may go unmaintained&lt;/strong&gt; (reported by 5 people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;take-away-message&quot;&gt;Take away message&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casual contributors&lt;/strong&gt; can see that they are not alone, and this behavior is, in fact, rather common in OSS communities. Also, we found that 22.93% of the casual contributions changed a single line of code. Thus, a developer does not need to be shy to contribute, even though her contribution is small. Yet,  this study revealed that project maintainers believe that casual contributions are a healthy way of contributing to OSS. Therefore, casual contributors can become even more motivated to do this kind of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project owners&lt;/strong&gt; can label tasks specific for casual contributors. Similarly, some casual contributors are more comfortable on solving low effort tasks. Thus, project owners can create specific roles for casual contributors (&lt;strong&gt;e.g.&lt;/strong&gt;, casual translators), which could also foster more engagement. Finally, since several projects maintainers do not have enough time to review casual contributions, they can introduce &amp;quot;contributions guidelines&amp;quot;, so that newcomers can read and get acquainted with them, therefore reducing code review effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2016/01/01/the-story-behind-casual-contributors.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2016/01/01/the-story-behind-casual-contributors.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Do developers care about software energy consumption?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Is energy consumption a real issue in the software development process? Do developer really care about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions were the start point of our paper, &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.github.io/lost+found/msr2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Mining Questions About Software Energy Consumption&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. In this paper, we investigated several questions about software energy consumption. Since we believe that research needs to be grounded in practice, we analyzed StackOverflow, one of the most famus software development web site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We filter out all questions that contain at least one energy consumption related word (&lt;em&gt;e.g.,&lt;/em&gt; energy efficiency). After this process, we found 615 question, but after removing false positives, we ended up with only 325  valid questions. We used a qualitative approach to analyze these questions, named &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thematic_analysis&quot;&gt;Thematic Analysis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyzing such questions, we observed that practitioners are aware of the energy consumption problems: the questions they ask are not only diverse -- we found 5 main themes of questions -- but also often more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;challenging&lt;/em&gt; when compared to the remaining questions on StackOverflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found five main themes regarding energy consumption questions. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurements&lt;/strong&gt;. Questions about measurement tools or techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Questions that do not have a concrete use case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code Design&lt;/strong&gt;. Questions about programming techniques that can help in saving energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context-specific&lt;/strong&gt;. The authors of such questions need to provide more details in order for other users to better understand the problem, and to facilitate replication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise&lt;/strong&gt;. These questions are not directly associated with an energy consumption issue. Usually, the user first wants to improve one aspect of her application and, as a secondary goal, also improve energy consumption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since questions in the Code Design theme are usually focused on how programmer decisions may improve energy consumption, we believe that the Code Design category is the most important one for future energy-aware software development. This category is also the most popular among developers. In a in-depth analysis of this theme, we identified 8 solutions that developers use in order to save energy. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep IO to a minimum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bulk operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid Polling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware Coordination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurrent programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lazy Initialization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Race to Idle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient Data structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also observed that some reseachers support such solutions proposed by software developers. However, for some of them, like concurrent programming, solutions cannot be seen as one-size-fits-all, since no consensus has emerged from the relationship between concurrent programming, performance and energy consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, this study serves as a research agenda for future energy consumption research. The needs of developers and the challenges they face may help energy-efficiency researchers stay focused on the real-world problems. The collective wisdom shared by developers may serve as a practical guide for future energy- aware and energy-efficient software development. The conceptually incorrect views they hold may inspire educators to develop more state-of-the-art curricula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details, please check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.github.io/lost+found/msr2014.pdf&quot;&gt;our paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2014/11/25/do-developers-care-about-software-energy-consumption.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2014/11/25/do-developers-care-about-software-energy-consumption.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Why do you keep doing surveys?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;When I say survey, I mean online questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. I do like surveys. Actually, I have done few of them in my premature researcher career. And I think that we can keep conducting surveys; but I believe that we now have other good options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys are good when you have a specific, and small, target population. For example, if you want to know what the rails core developers eat on lunch, survey is definitely the way to go. But, what do you do if you want know what the rails community eat on lunch?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course, you can do a survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, there are some concerns that you have to keep in mind: First, survey has its own problems (the subject may lie in a difficult questions, or may remember incorrectly about a long time question, or may not fully understand a question and then give a faulty response). Second, the survey response rate is pretty low. If you are a luck guy, you can get 10% or 15% of response rate. So, if you are targeting the entire rails population, you may draw conclusions from a biased part of it. And finally, you may have to wait for several weeks (months?) until you have collected enough data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can simply change your data source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are doing computer science research, you have on hand a number of great on line data sources. All you have to do is pick up the right one, use your programming skill to extract the data, and proceed to the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know what rails core developers eat at lunch? Find them on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and mine their actives on there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know if developers are facing problems with the newest rails feature? Mine questions and answers about this topic on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stackoverflow.com&quot;&gt;StackOverfow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know if projects are moving to the newest rails version? Mine ruby/rails projects on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sourceforge.com&quot;&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;, and parse their source code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know if final users are facing energy consumption problems in mobile applications? Mine &lt;a href=&quot;http://play.google.com&quot;&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt; comments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see? Surveys are good. But, you can get a ton of data if you mine such websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, mining software repositories is not only about software, but human behaviour as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/12/03/Why-keep-doing-surveys.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/12/03/Why-keep-doing-surveys.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Tips to attend OOPSLA with low budget</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a [under]grad student who is wondering how amazing it could be to attend a flagship conference such as OOPSLA? But, as a student, you might have a low budget, right? If so, I may have some tips to share with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this year (2013) I attended my very first OOPSLA. It was awesome. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/394562681253810176&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/395050744291659776&quot;&gt;shared&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/395210719022436352&quot;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/395683470971641856&quot;&gt;stories&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/396020564361371648&quot;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/396021132479827969&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;. However, one of the things that made it so great was because I didn&amp;#39;t needed to pay anything. Neither my advisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it could be possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I basically follow three steps: (i) submit a paper to ACM SRC, (ii) apply to be a student volunteer, and (iii) request PAC funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll briefly describe these steps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider submitting a paper to ACM SRC&lt;/strong&gt;: One good reason to go to a conference is to give a talk about your reasearch (hopefully, in the main track of the conference). In this case, you will probably get money from your advisor/department/university. But, if you are on the early stages of your research, or if you got rejected, you can also consider submitting to the ACM SRC track. The goal of the ACM SRC is to facilitate interaction between researchers and practitioners, providing both sides the opportunity to learn of ongoing research. Additionally, the ACM SRC gives students experience with both formal presentations and evaluations. Finally, you can receive up to $ 500 to spend on your trip. Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apply to be a student volunteer&lt;/strong&gt;: When you are a student volunteer, you don&amp;#39;t need to pay for your registration. You could eventually receive other interesting things, such as a costumed t-shirt, or an invitation to a fancy dinner. &lt;strong&gt;Update: Student Volunteers for OOPSLA&amp;#39;2014 also received free hotel&lt;/strong&gt;. On the other hand, you have to work during the conference. Some duties include: help in the registration process, help inside the rooms, or help speakers/attends to find their rooms. But, don&amp;#39;t worry. You will find time to enjoy the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Request PAC funding&lt;/strong&gt;: Finally, if you have a paper accepted in one conference sponsored by SGIPLAN, you can also request funding from PAC. Note that not all conferences are sponsored by SIGPLAN. The ACM SRC, for example, is not sponsored. However, the SPLASH/Poster sesssion is sponsored. These two tracks happens together at SPLASH. Also, if you don&amp;#39;t have any paper accepted, but was accepted to be a student volunteer, you can also request PAC funding. That is great, hun? And it is pretty easy to apply. You just have to fill up a form, explaing how do you plan to spend this money.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, these were my tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I&amp;#39;m not sure if you can follow these steps if you are planing to attend other top-tier conference. It works for OOPSLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all. I hope to see you at SPLASH/OOPSLA&amp;#39;2014 in Portland :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/11/01/tips-to-attend-oopsla-with-low-budget.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/11/01/tips-to-attend-oopsla-with-low-budget.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Pycon 2014 - Call for posters</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;PyCon is the premier Python Conference, and in 2014 it is being held for the first very time outside US - in the beautify Montéal/CA. It is not only a great opportunity to met the best python programmers across the world, but also to make the PyCon even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about presenting a poster in the Python premier conference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-does-it-work?&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a presenter, you get to interact directly with your audience, share your passion and your idea, and immediately address questions in a more conversational manner. Moreover, the environment is generally less stressful and more easygoing than giving a formal talk. On top of that, you met a lot of interesting people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is to present your topic on a 4&amp;#39;x4&amp;#39; poster board and as attendees mingle through the rows, they find your topic, read through what you have written, the strike up a discussion on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users of all levels go to the poster session, so your topic can focus on novice, intermediate or even expert programmers. Focus on what you think is interesting, rather than difficult/complex. This video will give you an idea of what poster sessions are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-kind-of-proposal-can-i-submit?&quot;&gt;What kind of proposal can I submit?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering about what kind of python stuff you will be able to talk. As an advice, we can told you that you can talk about anything you want to. Don&amp;#39;t be shy. We would love hear what make you exciting with Python. But, if the problem is missing ideas, why don&amp;#39;t take a look in the poster section of &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.pycon.org/2013/schedule/posters/list/&quot;&gt;PyCon&amp;#39;13&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.pycon.org/2012/schedule/lists/posters/&quot;&gt;PyCon&amp;#39;12&lt;/a&gt;? People made an incredible work in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hmm..-i&amp;#39;m-interested.-how-to-submit-a-proposal?&quot;&gt;Hmm.. I&amp;#39;m interested. How to submit a proposal?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To submit a poster proposal, you should first create an account in the PyCon site. When you are logged in, you will need to include the following information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The title of your post&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The category&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intended audience (assumed level of knowledge)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A brief description - 300 chars max&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A detailed description&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional notes for the proposal reviewers. This can include additional background information such as links to other presentations you have done, or links to blog posts, articles or code related to your presentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that the posters should follow all of the usual &lt;a href=&quot;http://us.pycon.org/2014/speaking/proposal_advice/&quot;&gt;guidelines&lt;/a&gt; that we look for in talk and tutorial proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;important-dates&quot;&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not miss the application deadline!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poster submission deadline: November 1st, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poster announced: December 15th, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poster session at PyCon&amp;#39;14: April 13th, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need more information, you can see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://us.pycon.org/2014/posters/faq/&quot;&gt;Poster FAQ&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.pycon.org/2014/posters/&quot;&gt;Poster CFP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We look forward to seeing you in Montreal in 2014!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/07/19/pycon-2014-call-for-poster.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/07/19/pycon-2014-call-for-poster.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>From where come the Brazilian open-source contributions?</title>
				<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;from-where-come-the-brazilian-open-source-contributions?&quot;&gt;From where come the Brazilian open-source contributions?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days ago I was wondering why open-source communities are so cool! You can meet a lot of interesting people, who devote a lot time of their time-lifes just to create stuffs that other people will use. It is strange. Usually, this people actually have their own business, work, family, whatever, and they still find time to work for free. It sounds weird to me (even though I devote part of my time to open-source activities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the point is: how active these communities are? And if you take into consideration only the Brazilian community, what is the general picture that we can drawn from they? Thinking about it, I collected a lot of data about Brazilian developers in the github social coding website. There is a lot of interesting findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;1. Are the brazilian open-source community active&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as I expected. I gathered data for a total of 4.481 users, which 3.121 ones do not have any kind of contribution. That is, 30% of the users (the active group) are responsible for 100% of the contribution. The active group was sub-divided in more three groups: low active (up to 19 contribution per year),  fairly active (up to 49 contributions per year) and very active (more than 49 contributions per year). Furthermore, the percentage of the low actives, fairly actives and very actives are, respectively, 57.8%, 20.9%, 21.3%. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&quot;&gt;Pareto&amp;#39;s principle&lt;/a&gt; also works here: from 30% of the users come the 100% of the contributions. This results show us that the brazilian open-source community is not so active as we may guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/post3/users-active-percentage.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2. From where they come?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take into consideration the user locale, we observed that 46% of these users come from the Northeast region, which is very interesting, since, here in Brazil, the most economical region (or, in this case, from where have the most job offers) is the southeast region. If we take into consideration the specific State, the most active are Paraná (13.65%), followed by Ceará (12.37%) and followed by (11.25%). All theses states are not part of the southeast region. Nonetheless, this kind of analysis is very difficult to perform, since the user can omit the location field (which represents 8% of the total), provide unreliable information, or use acronym, nicknames, etc. But, if we can draw a chart of the Brazilian open-source contribution per state, it may look like this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/post3/total_commits.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;3. Which are the most popular programming languages?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github can infer the most used language on a given project. Then, analyzing the set of projects contributed, the list of the ten more used programming language are: JavaScript (22.77%), Ruby (18.78%), Java (14.19%), PHP (13.95%), Python (9.86%), C (3.36%), C++ (2.94%), Shell (2.55%), Objective-C (1.95%) e C# (1.88%). I have to tell that these results surprised me a bit. Since I&amp;#39;m a Java-guy, my heart used to fell that Java is the most popular language in Brazil. But, it seems that Brazilian hackers are more likely to use untyped languages, such as JS, Ruby, PHP, although the Java language remains in the top-3. It is cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;#39;m wondering if these data are only related to github, or if it could be possible to generalize. Someday I want to correlate this result with stackoverflow, or other similar forge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more about, please check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.github.io/lost+found/oss2014.pdf&quot;&gt;our paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/07/19/from-where-come-the-brazilian-open-source-contributions.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/07/19/from-where-come-the-brazilian-open-source-contributions.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Improving our line plots with R</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may know, I&amp;#39;m a graduate student and part of my work is spent on writing papers. And, frequently, these papers contains a lot of charts. As long as I&amp;#39;m a graduate student, I&amp;#39;m very disapointed with the charts that open-office plots. Specially, the line charts. It is kinda a four-years-old-children playing with their paint and brush. Do not believe? Take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/post2/usage-per-thread.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yesterday I really decided to revert this game. Surfing on the internet, I read some people writing that R is outstanding to ploting charts, which I had serious doubts, mainly because I have been using R for a long time. But, most of the time is to plot boxplot, or to use few functions such as &lt;code&gt;summary&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sd&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cor&lt;/code&gt;, among more two or three. Not less, not more. In my (naive) imagination, R should had a function like &lt;code&gt;plotanincrediblechart&lt;/code&gt;, and I only should pass the data array. But R does not have this function. In fact, R has a number of functions, and, when you play with they together, you can get a nice chart like the this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/post2/usage-per-thread-r.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much better, uh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can you do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;first&quot;&gt;First&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start by initializing your data array. If you do not have basic knowledge in R, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/doc/contrib/Paradis-rdebuts_en.pdf&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; is a good start point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-R&quot; data-lang=&quot;R&quot;&gt;seq &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;78&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;78&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;78&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;78&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
thread &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;60&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;55&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
executors &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;56&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
forkJoin &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;79&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;55&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;52&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;54&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
actors &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;82&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;47&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;38&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;second&quot;&gt;Second&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a simple line chart with one of your data set using the &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; function. In this case, I used the &lt;code&gt;thread&lt;/code&gt; var.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-R&quot; data-lang=&quot;R&quot;&gt;plot&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;thread&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; type&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;o&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pch&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; ylim&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this function, we passed the &lt;code&gt;thread&lt;/code&gt; var and more four arguments. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt;: the plot type;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;col&lt;/code&gt;: the line color (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://research.stowers-institute.org/efg/R/Color/Chart/ColorChart.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see all colors avaiable in R);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;pch&lt;/code&gt;: the vector of plotting characters or symbols;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ylim&lt;/code&gt;: the y limits of the plot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several other parameters that you can use in your chart. If you have the time, take a lot at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/graphics/html/plot.default.html&quot;&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we have to add the remaining data. To do so, we will use another function called &lt;code&gt;lines&lt;/code&gt;. In this example, we pass five arguments to this function. Note that these arguments are the same ones that we have passed to the &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; function. Therefore, for each new vector that you want to plot, you have to add a new line, such as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-R&quot; data-lang=&quot;R&quot;&gt;lines&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; type&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;o&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pch&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; lty&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;darkred&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
lines&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;executors&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; type&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;o&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pch&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; lty&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;purple&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
lines&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;forkJoin&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; type&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;o&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pch&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; lty&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;chocolate3&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
lines&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;actors&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; type&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;o&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; pch&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; lty&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; col&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;orangered2 &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;code&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;pre&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the moment, your chart may looks like this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/post2/middle-chart.png&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! Our chart is becoming professional. My mon will be proud of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;third&quot;&gt;Third&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third part is to add both vertical and horizontal lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;abline(v=1,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=1.5,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=2,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=2.5,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=3,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=3.5,col=1,lty=3)
abline(v=4,col=1,lty=3)

abline(h=100,col=1,lty=3)
abline(h=80,col=1,lty=3)
abline(h=60,col=1,lty=3)
abline(h=40,col=1,lty=3)
abline(h=20,col=1,lty=3)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that, we first add the vertical lines, and then, the horizontal lines. We differ each other by the first parameter (&lt;code&gt;v&lt;/code&gt; for vertical lines and &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; for horizontal lines). The second parameter, as you might guess, is the color of the line, and the last one is the line type. Line types can either be specified as an integer (0=blank, 1=solid, ...) or as one of the character strings &amp;quot;blank&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;solid&amp;quot;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fourth&quot;&gt;Fourth&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth and finally part is to plot a box with the lines information. To this, you will need two functions: &lt;code&gt;box&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;legend&lt;/code&gt;. I think the name of these functions are meaningful. But, the &lt;code&gt;legend&lt;/code&gt; function receives several parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;box()
labels &lt;- c(&quot;Sequential&quot;,&quot;Thread&quot;, &quot;Executors&quot;, &quot;ForkJoin&quot;, &quot;Scala Actors&quot;)
colors &lt;- c(&quot;blue&quot;,&quot;darkred&quot;, &quot;purple&quot;, &quot;chocolate3&quot;, &quot;orangered2&quot;)
pch &lt;- c(18,23,24,25,8)

legend(1.0, 50, labels, cex=0.8, col=colors, pch=phc, lty=1,bg = &quot;white&quot;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you&amp;#39;ll probably see a very similar chart like the second topmost in this post. All code is pasted &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/gustavopinto/5570951&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And, that is it! :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you later alligator!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/05/08/improving-your-line-plots-with-r.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/05/08/improving-your-line-plots-with-r.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Hello World</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my new Blog: The codefather. Here I plan to discuss mainly about programming languages and code design in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-the-name&quot;&gt;About the name&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, as you can imagine, the name is a joke with the Godfather movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;/images/codefather.jpg&#39;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/04/07/hello-world.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://gustavopinto.org/codefather/2013/04/07/hello-world.html</guid>
			</item>
			
		
	</channel>
</rss>
