<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-04T11:16:38-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gustavo Pinto</title><subtitle>Soft Eng Professor and Researcher</subtitle><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><entry><title type="html">How to write a short book in 20 hours</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/How-to-write-a-short-book-in-20-hours/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to write a short book in 20 hours" /><published>2020-04-28T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-28T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/How-to-write-a-short-book-in-20-hours</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/How-to-write-a-short-book-in-20-hours/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/1-5-good-habits-for-young-scholars-9d11c8ca2410&quot;&gt;I wrote a short book in 20 hours.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the best book I could write? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It this book really well-written? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you proud of this book? Definitely yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-background&quot;&gt;Some background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in the middle of a pandemic that is only getting worse. I have two small kids at home that require a lot of me. I only have the evenings free when they are already sleeping. I wrote for four evenings, about 2–4 hours every evening. I started writing on Thursday and finished on Sunday. Also, on Sunday I made the cover. On Monday morning, I started selling. I sell eight copies in the first day ($ 5 each).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-wrote-this-book&quot;&gt;Why I wrote this book?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many reasons motivated me to write this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I have been thinking about writing a book for many years. I actually already started to write one book in the past, but I gave up not much later. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing-52b977091718&quot;&gt;For those that follow me on twitter, they may know that I am writing another book on open source licensing.&lt;/a&gt; But I thought I need another book to be ready sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, because I am in the middle of a pandemic, and I am feeling incapable of doing anything useful. I have already canceled some research works because neither my students nor I can commit to them anymore (&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/got-tenure-what-does-it-mean-e0afa94e1bc6&quot;&gt;yes, I know I’m privileged&lt;/a&gt;). Many relatives, friends, and colleagues are suffering from this pandemic, and I can barely do anything to help them. I like my work, but I don’t see my work being anyhow useful to help them overcome this immediate situation. Nevertheless, I’m seeing many colleagues who are finding a way to help others, for instance, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ccsl.ufpa.br/covid-19/&quot;&gt;by creating tools that could increase the pandemic awareness&lt;/a&gt;. I eventually made some donations here and there, but, unfortunately, I cannot commit to these regular donations next month without compromising my family budget. Then I had the idea of writing a book and donating 100% of the sales to help COVID-19. My little experience &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing-52b977091718&quot;&gt;pre-selling the other book&lt;/a&gt; opened my eyes that it’s possible to sell books on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, having this plan in mind, the last point was to decide what I could write about (and very quickly). It did not take much to realize that I could write about &lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/gustavopinto/caminhos-e-desafios-para-a-pesquisa-em-computacao-ou-como-se-manter-produtivo-na-regiao-norte&quot;&gt;one of the talks that I gave in the past&lt;/a&gt;. First because I believe the talk was well-received (both in-person and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/1202323018762117120?s=20&quot;&gt;on-line&lt;/a&gt;). Second, because I was already thinking about putting the ideas of that talk in a blog post. However, I knew it would require me many hours to do it, so I was keeping postponing. By converting this blog post in a book motivated me to make it happen. And really fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-write-it&quot;&gt;How did I write it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, I did not have much time to write this book. I decided to write the book on Thursday, April 23rd, and I was willing to compromise to make it available on Monday, 27th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first step was to find a book template. In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing-52b977091718&quot;&gt;other book&lt;/a&gt;, I have already spent some good hours fighting with a template (and I still don’t like my current template). To write the other book, I’m using asciidoctor, a framework that exports documents to many writing formats. To save some hours, for this book, I decided to use LaTeX instead. I’m reasonably familiar with LaTeX, so I would not wast any time configuring it, running it, etc. I also knew there are some excellent LaTeX templates out there, so it was not hard to find a one I liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this book was about a talk I gave in the past, I have the structure already designed in my mind. I used the same structure of the talk to structure the book. On the first evening, I wrote the preface, and the first two chapters (around 2.5k words). The preface I rewrote in the end, but I did not make substantial changes in the first two chapters after my first pass. I kept the same progress over Friday and Saturday (about 2k words per day). The book was 90% on Saturday. On Sunday, I made an overall pass, trying to fixing some typos and strange wordings. Also, on Sunday, I made the cover (using canva.com), and I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/1-5-good-habits-for-young-scholars-9d11c8ca2410&quot;&gt;a blog post to share the book on social networks&lt;/a&gt;. I already shared this blog post on hackernews and reddit on Sunday evening. On Monday morning, I wrote some tweets to release the book to the public. I made eight sales on the first day on Twitter and no sales through the other mediums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-than-20-hours&quot;&gt;More than 20 hours&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the title of this blog post is correct, upon reflection, I spent many more hours working on this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, because I probably spent 20 hours or so designing and creating the talk. When thinking about the talk, I took several notes, made some sketches, and also did some research. After that, I spent some good hours creating the talk on Keynote. Till minutes before the talk, I was making changes in the slides. I also spent 2–3 hours rehearsing the talk, which gave me additional ideas. When writing this book, I took for granted the time I spent thinking about and creating the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, because I also took for granted what I learned in the past. For instance, I did not have to do much research on the topic (it was fresh on my mind), and I did not need to master the tools used (it took 10 minutes to have a book template and about 30 minutes to have a cover).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be a different story I had to write about a subject that I am not super comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s also important to notice that, as a researcher, a good proportion of my job is devoted to writing. I have been writing a lot over the last 10 years lot, so I’m used to technical writing. I’m not a fluent writer (I am not fluent in English either), but writing is not a big issue to me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">A short book</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1+5 Good Habits for Young Scholars</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/1-5-Good-Habits-for-Young-Scholars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1+5 Good Habits for Young Scholars" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Good-Habits-for-Young-Scholars</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/1-5-Good-Habits-for-Young-Scholars">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gum.co/good-research-habits&quot;&gt;I’m selling about good habits that young scholars could foster while finding their path in academia, for only $ 5&lt;/a&gt;. 100% of the sales will go to a hospital fighting COVID-19. Read on to know more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academia could be a wonderful place. By seeking the truth, researchers are exposed to several research challenges, and their discoveries could shape the way we think, work, and live. However, academia can also be a tough place to work. Graduate students are six times more likely to be depressed than the general population. The academic job market is extremely competitive. 
If you happen to think that academia is for you, it is better to foster some good habits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book that &lt;a href=&quot;http://gum.co/good-research-habits&quot;&gt;I’m selling for only $ 5&lt;/a&gt;, I describe 1+5 habits that I cultivate and follow over the last few years. By sharing this habits, I believe I could help other young scholars to find their path in academia, as I found mine. The 1+5 habits are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do your homework;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know your institution;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procrastinate on Twitter;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay health;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/qoy0t21l4kxazo2/sample.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;There is a sample of the book, including the chapter that describes the first habit.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A natural question that the reader would ask is: why you mention 1+5 habits instead of just six habits? Well, because I believe the first one is not a habit, but an obligation. If you don’t do your homework, you can hardly move forward. Therefore, the other habits do not make much sense. Simple like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;100-of-the-sales-to-combatcovid-19&quot;&gt;100% of the sales to combat COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first 90 days, I will donate 100% of the sales to UFPA hospitals that are in the front line fighting COVID-19 (excluding taxes and fees). I will make everything transparent in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gustavopinto.org/books/good-rearch-habits/&quot;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;limitations&quot;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In research works, we always have many limitations. This book is no different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, one avid reader would quickly realize that the writer of this book is a young researcher himself, so his habits might be limited due to his little experience in conducting research projects. I wholeheartedly concur. Therefore, this book may be more attractive to really young scholars, such as undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I cannot claim that the ideas that I discuss in this document are anything new. On the contrary, many have been discussed since the early days of research and documented in many books by many authors in many research fields. Perhaps, the main benefit of this book is to have these ideas summarized in a single place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, as a software engineering professor and researcher, my views are shaped based on my interactions with this community. Although I believe that some researchers in other areas could see some value here and there, it is not clear to me how my “1+5 habits” would generalize to other research fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this book is based on my own experience and views. It does not reflect the opinions of my employer, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-theauthor&quot;&gt;About the author&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gustavo Pinto is a software engineering researcher and professor at the Federal University of Pará, Brazil. Gustavo Pinto is a young scholar himself. He got his Ph.D. from the Federal University of Pernambuco, Brazil, in 2015. Since them, he became a fairly active researcher in his research community, which could be noticed by his 60+ papers published, 1,000+ citations, and five awards. Know more online at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gustavopinto.org&quot;&gt;www.gustavopinto.org&lt;/a&gt; or follow him on Twitter (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/gustavopinto&quot;&gt;@gustavopinto&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">Promoting a book</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why the MIT licensed is 18x more used then GPL-3?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Why-the-MIT-licensed-is-18x-more-used-then-GPL-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why the MIT licensed is 18x more used then GPL-3?" /><published>2020-04-20T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Why-the-MIT-licensed-is-18x-more-used-then-GPL-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Why-the-MIT-licensed-is-18x-more-used-then-GPL-3/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot;&gt;I am writing a book to make open source licensing easier to understand!&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gumroad.com/js/gumroad.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;gumroad-button&quot; href=&quot;https://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I want this!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are dozens or even hundreds of open source licenses available out there. More generally speaking, these licenses can be grouped in two groups: permissive licenses and restrictive licenses. On the permissive group, perhaps the MIT license is one of the most common one. On the other group, GPL is one of the most important restrictive licenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one is the most common used in open source projects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the question is easy to pose, it is not necessarily easy to answer, mainly because the multiple threats hidden when analyzing license usage in open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First because there is not a single coding hosting website that hosts all open source projects. Although GitHub is one of the most common alternatives, many open source projects are hosted in the community git repository, in other repositories such as the Debian package archive, and GNU Project FTP archive, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, because in order to understand open source license usage in scale, we should rely on tools that infer the license used. This process is not always precise because developers often state open source licenses in different ways. For example, while some developers declare their licenses as a comment in the header of every source code file, other developers just cite the license used for the whole project within the README file. Moreover, some developers copy and paste the full text of the license, whereas other developers might only mention the name of the license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these limitation, we could still try to infer the open source license usage in practice by, for instance, using GitHub data stored on Libraries.io (an service that curates metadata from open source projects hosted in several package managers). Libraries.io provides data  available on Zenodo. Using this data, we inferred license usage as one could be see next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Using &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/librariesio?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@librariesio&lt;/a&gt; data to investigate the most common open source licenses used in practice.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Permissive licenses (MIT, Apache, BSD) are by far the most used ones. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Want to know why and the implications behind this? Consider supporting this book ~&amp;gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/WBQzzxP1oK&quot;&gt;https://t.co/WBQzzxP1oK&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/nkozzNw643&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/nkozzNw643&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gustavo Pinto (@gustavopinto) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/1251939815488135173?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one could see, permissive licenses are by far the most used one. Indeed, MIT is the most used license, appearing in more than 812k open source projects. Apache 2.0 comes next, appearing in 465k projects. BSD-3, also a permissive license, appears next, licensing 71k projects. These three licenses (MIT, Apache 2.0, and BSD-3) are used in about 70% of the overall open source license usage. On the other spectrum of this figure, one could see that the GPL family of licenses (GPL-2, GPL-3, AGPL-3, LGPL-3) comprehends around only 5% of the overall license usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-this-happening&quot;&gt;Why is this happening?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a 2016 survey with about 3,400 participants, it is estimated that 67% of the surveyed companies actively encourage developers to engage in and contribute to open source software. This shows a clear commercial interest in open source projects. However, some researchers also believe that GPL is not the most appropriated choice for a business that relies on open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though software licensed under GPL can be used (and even modified) in corporate environments, software companies should be aware of the characteristics of GPL. In particular, the key feature of GPL is that it restricts the terms of distribution of derived works. If any software company incorporates any source code licensed under GPL, the company must license the software products it sells that use GPL code under GPL as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GPL, created by the Free Software Foundation (FSF), is the principal copyleft license. The GPL license has the ultimate goal of making software 100% free for everyone. This decision of going 100% free is actually a challenge for business that may not always could support providing 100% of their code to the public (for instance, have you ever seen the actual Google implementation of its search engine?). As a consequence, some business might be not comfortable in using a license that is very aligned with such goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know more about open source licensing and some hidden problems behind it? Please consider supporting my book on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gumroad.com/l/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot;&gt;Demystifying Open Source Licensing&lt;/a&gt;, to be self-published in late July 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">GPL restricts the terms of distribution of derived works’</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What can go wrong when one misuses open source licenses?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/what-can-go-wrong-when-one-misuses-open-source-licenses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What can go wrong when one misuses open source licenses?" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/what-can-go-wrong-when-one-misuses-open-source-licenses</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/what-can-go-wrong-when-one-misuses-open-source-licenses/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot;&gt;I am writing a book to make open source licensing easier to understand!&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gumroad.com/js/gumroad.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;gumroad-button&quot; href=&quot;https://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I want this!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open source licenses create a legal framework that play key role on the widespread adoption of open source projects. Any open source project must be released under one (or more) open source license. Without a license, any source code available on the internet could not be openly (re)distributed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a natural consequence, open source licenses is one of the most important non-executable piece of any open source software project. Open source licenses not only drive how one can use an OSS but also ensure to what extent others can reuse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, due to its non-technical nature, developers often misuse or misunderstand open source licenses. I believe there are at least &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; reasons that may justify this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the vocabulary used in open source licenses are not part of the developers daily vocabulary, so it may require developers to gain additional knowledge to understand software licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there are hundreds of open source licenses readily available for developers use. Indeed, many of these licenses are quite similar, differing by just one or two minor changes in the license text. Since developers are always busy, they might have very limited time to catch and understand these corner cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, many of the text books about open source licensing devote a good proportion of the document to explain the concepts, ideas, and differences between the existing open source licenses. However, developers might also have a hard time relating how these abstractions could make any sense in their daily activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book I argue that the lack of a clear understanding of software licensing could challenge the existence of any open source software project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give the reader one example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, one of the core maintainers of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lerna/lerna/&quot;&gt;Lerna&lt;/a&gt; project decided to change a bit the license. The maintainer made a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lerna/lerna/pull/1616&quot;&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; that changed the used MIT license to include &lt;em&gt;restrictive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;retroactive&lt;/em&gt; clauses to users of the Lerna project. With this pull-request, tech companies such as Microsoft, Amazon, Dell, Xerox, Canon, LinkedIn, and few other were not allowed to use Lerna to support their software development activities anymore. The maintainer went further and described that the motivation to perform this change was because these tech companies were collaborating with the US Immigration and Customs Enforcement (“ICE”). On his views, “these companies care only about the millions of dollars that ICE is paying them and are willing to ignore all the horrible things that ICE does.” Although one might think that there are good intentions behind these changes, there are also two problems hidden on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, by restricting the use of the software to certain groups of users, the Lerna would actually be discriminating them. However, non-discrimination is a core value of open source. According to the fifth clause of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.org/osd-annotated&quot;&gt;Open Source Definition&lt;/a&gt;, the “license must not discriminate against any person or group of persons”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, there is no such thing such as a retroactive license change. Yes, you can change the license, but it would only work for new users, using the new release of your open source software. You cannot change a license expecting the existing users would be affected. These existing users could keep using the old version of your software (with the previous license), and this is just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This single pull-request had several repercussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Raymond, the author of the famous “The Cathedral and the Bazaar” and one of the creators of the Open Source Initiative, also shared &lt;a href=&quot;http://esr.ibiblio.org/?p=8106&quot;&gt;his views&lt;/a&gt; about this problem. He said that “The Lerna project’s choice is, moreover, destructive of one of the deep norms that keeps the open-source community functional – keeping politics separated from our work”. Open source developers, when not coding, are free do to whatever they want. It does not matter for the code if the developer supports ICE or a far right wing party. By mixing politics with open source, through the (mis)use of its license, the whole chain of users of the Lerna project was impacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long story short: the pull-request was reverted, the maintainer was banned from the project, and the open source community around Lerna was hurted. All of this due to 22 lines added in the license file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1st Lessons learned: It’s possible to change a license, but these changes should not discriminate any person or group or field of endeavor. Moreover, it is not possible to change a license retroactively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to know more about open source licensing and some hidden problems behind it? Please consider supporting my book on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gumroad.com/l/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot;&gt;Demystifying Open Source Licensing&lt;/a&gt;, to be self-published in late July 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">It can be bad</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Book: Demystifying Open Source Licensing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Book: Demystifying Open Source Licensing" /><published>2020-04-13T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-13T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/new-book-demystifying-open-source-licensing/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing&quot;&gt;I am writing a book to make open source licensing easier to understand!&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an open source user and software engineering researcher, I have been amazed about how tricky this topic is and how easy things can go wrong.
If you are a developer, you should definitively understand a bit more about open source licenses. Why is it important to study open source licenses in 2020? Some questions to think:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know why Google banned the use of the AGPL license  on any of  its open source projects?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know why GPL 2.0 license, one of the purest copyleft licenses around, has more than halved in usage in the last 10 years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know why it took about one year to change a license in the Eclipse project?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know that one of the core maintainers of Lerna project was removed from the core team due to license misuses?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you know that you should run away from open source projects that don’t have any license?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software licensing is a complex subject, which often requires expertise from other other areas far away from the software development arena. Indeed, most books regarding software licensing are also written by lawyers, which is not a problem itself, but the terms employed may hinder the understand of the software development community (I had a hard time understanding these books). Another problem is that developers may not always see any concrete implication of an eventual license misuse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this book is two-fold: First, we intend to make this complex license stuff simpler. Second, the book should highlight concrete examples of license problems (so developers could easily relate to their activities). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this, we expect that developers could better understand the importance of open source licenses and the context in which they could use or not one given software library (because of license concerns). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is intended to be short (~100 pages) and will be ready around June, but it is open for pre-orders, for only $ 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##For whom this book is for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are are developer and have to use open source software on daily basis, &lt;strong&gt;this book is for you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are project maintainer and still struggle to understand what license you should use, &lt;strong&gt;this book is for you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are a researcher interested in studying open source licensing issues, &lt;strong&gt;this book is for you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you care about open source, but don’t really understand open source licensing, &lt;strong&gt;this book is for you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;got-interested&quot;&gt;Got interested?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this interests you, it would mean a lot if you pre-order your copy, online at https://gum.co/demystifying-oss-licensing You will receive the final book in your inbox as soon as it’s ready. If open source is not your thing, you could also help by sharing this blog post with your friends 🙏🏻&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you happen to not like the book, just reply to the download email within 30 days, and you’ll get a full refund. No question asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will keep sharing my progress in writing this book on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gustavopinto&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow on if you want to be updated! &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">I am writing a book to make open source licensing easier to understand! </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lack of focus in Academia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lack-of-focus-in-academia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lack of focus in Academia" /><published>2020-04-11T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-11T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lack-of-focus-in-academia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lack-of-focus-in-academia/">&lt;p&gt;Academia is an interesting place. After a lot of training during your undergrad and grad studies, you are thrown in a pool and are asked to swim to find your own research agenda. Find unique and relevant questions that no one else has contribute before. Work tirelessly to answer them. Become an expert on a this very narrow field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture is often times reinforced by the tenure track process of many research intensive institutions. That is, to get your tenure, you are expected to become a world-wide leader on your research area. As a consequence, researchers working towards their tenure should have at least two things in mind: first, they should choose wisely the research area in which they intend to do a contribution (something fun and interesting that could make their eyes open for some years) and, second, they should have the discipline to commit their work to this subject, while not placing too much effort on stuff that (although interesting) may not concretely contribute to their tenure assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is: although you have the freedom to explore uncharted research territories, you should not explore several different research topics. In other words, you should not go in-breadth; you should go in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on I will describe my experience going in-breadth, but for now let’s consider going in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think going in-depth is harder, but also more valuable. Going in-depth requires vision and discipline. Vision is important to understand what are the unique and relevant problems that worth to be addressed. Vision also requires experience. Without experience, many low dead ends might be seen as promising research opportunities. However, discipline might be as important as, or even more important than, vision because, without discipline, one could easily change focus to contribute to something else. Discipline to commit to a far-reaching goal is perhaps one of the greatest skills a researcher might have. Notwithstanding, we all praise the efforts of those that have substantially contributed to a field over many years (or even many decades). It is hard to compromise and keep putting effort on a long term goal. On the other hand, it is easy to lose focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking a bit about my recent career as a research, I definitively went in-breadth instead of in-depth. This became even clearer after I recorded this 50s video about my research and shared on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m not part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/icse21?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#icse21&lt;/a&gt; OC but I liked this idea, and I’m sharing my research in 30s (or a bit more). &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/o34qKy5iQn&quot;&gt;https://t.co/o34qKy5iQn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/UxzG2pcr9T&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/UxzG2pcr9T&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gustavo Pinto (@gustavopinto) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gustavopinto/status/1249010040314507264?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 11, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video I mentioned that I work on some technical aspects of software, but I also have some interests on social aspects of software. Nice, but… isn’t it what software engineering is all about? Instead of talking about my very narrowed research field, I talked about software engineering in general. Not sure what Twitter folks got from this video, but definitely it was not a concrete research agenda. I have a really serious lack of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this lack of focus is not something new to me. When meeting new colleagues at conferences, I often have a hard time trying to explain what I do. My views about what constitutes an important research problem is also very limited, because I concentrate a lot of effort on the surface of several different problems, instead of digging deeper and deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Import to mention that this lack of focus, however, did not impact on my tenure evaluation. As I mentioned in another blog post, the tenure track process in Brazil is much lighter than the tenure track process in other countries. Although this did not place a tool on my permanence in academia, this is perhaps a good time to revisit this choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, however, I want to reflect why I chose to have this in-breadth research agenda. First of all, I did not choose going in-breadth. It was the condition that I found for keeping doing research. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I graduated, I spent a year working at IFPA. Afterwards I moved to UFPA, which I’m now on my third year of professoring. However, my first master student arrived only on my second year at UFPA. Moreover, only in 2020 that I started to supervise my first doctoral student. As a consequence, during these years, most of the work I did was on collaboration with other professors and (eventually) their students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I didn’t have students, I wanted to keep publishing. If someone invited me to participate in a research project, I pretty much accepted even before knowing what the research project was about. Following this strategy for 3 — 5 years, and then my research portfolio becomes a scattered picture of several different research agendas. Obviously, I also did many research works that were driven by my own interests, but in these cases I had to embrace all steps of the research process (which is hard to keep making process in the long term, when you have many other obligations fighting for your attention).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is: after going in-breadth for some years, I am now struggling to have an unique research topic. This is now becoming an important thing because I’m finally starting to foster my own research group (yes, it took some time…), and it makes sense to me to focus on fewer things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, due to my lack of clear research agenda, my students are working on several different topics. This brings many challenges, for instance: 1) I am not aware of the related work of many of these different research topics, then I often don’t know if what the student is doing is indeed novel, 2) I have a hard time trying to help students that are not making progress, because I’m not familiar with the low level implementation details, 3) students can hardly help each other, because their subjects are very different, 4) it is harder to contribute towards a bigger goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it took 3–5 years to build this scattered research agenda, it would be naive to expect any drastic change in the next few months. Instead, my plan is to gradually focus on this unique research agenda (which so far is not clear to me). Needless to say, it would require a lot of discipline to make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">Too many things to do</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Got tenure; What does it mean?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/got-tenure-what-does-it-mean/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Got tenure; What does it mean?" /><published>2020-04-04T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-04T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/got-tenure-what-does-it-mean</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/got-tenure-what-does-it-mean/">&lt;p&gt;As of April the 4th, 2020, I am a tenured professor at UFPA, Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brief disclaimer: the tenure track process in Brazil is very lightweight when compared to the tenure track in US or in Europe. Although we are evaluated in terms of teaching, research, and service, I think teaching is what really counts for tenure here. I think I would still be granted tenure even if I haven’t published any paper or haven’t made any service to the university or to the research community. If this is good or bad I’ll leave for another blog post. What really matters now is what changes it would bring to the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew about my promotion since the end of 2019, and since then I have been thinking what does this tenured position &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; mean. Am I supposed to change anything on my work?  If so, what do I need to change? What does it mean to have a tenure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I thought that tenure has to do with &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;. Freedom to explore any research area that I may find interesting, without worrying too much about whether it would lead to a paper published in a top notch journal. I also though about that tenure has to do with &lt;em&gt;responsibility&lt;/em&gt; to focus on hard problems (instead of problems that could lead to immediate publications). I also thought about &lt;em&gt;commitment&lt;/em&gt; to do the best work that I could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting point here is that all these thoughts are related to work (and the kind of work that I do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I happen to receive my tenure letter during the perhaps worst health and financial crisis since World War II. I happen to receive my tenure when billions of people are staying in home fighting for their lives. While staying at home, many of them were unable to make any money; while many of them are being fired from their jobs; while many of them are struggling to stay rational and healthy without income; while many of them are having a hard time to find a way to pay their thousands-of-dollars health insurance bills. I happen to receive my letter of permanent appointment when some long term industries worldwide are collapsing overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this moment, for me, receiving tenure means just one thing: &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do have the privilege of staying in home knowing that my pay check will arrive next month. I have the privilege of knowing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/its-ok-to-be-unproductive-during-covid-19-7a64406328db&quot;&gt;it’s OK to be unproductive during the crisis&lt;/a&gt;. Despite of that, I also have the privilege of knowing that it’s very unlikely that I’ll be fired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing that I am privileged, I should also acknowledge that whatever success I am achieve is not solely due to my own efforts, but also due to a system that supports me. For instance, I don’t need to worry about pay checks. I don’t need to worry about moving to another place in the middle of a pandemic because my contract is about to finish. Any other researcher under time-bound contracts may have much more worries than I do; then, they may struggle to perform at their best because of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is: what do I do with this privilege I have been given?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about this tenure privilege for a while. It makes little sense to me to keep working as usual, as if nothing had happened. I already wrote in the past about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@gustavopinto/changing-roles-in-the-academic-system-6c1470672054&quot;&gt;roles in the academic system&lt;/a&gt;, and that my current role is to &lt;em&gt;teach others to do research&lt;/em&gt;. I still agree. However, by broadening this a bit, I could see that my role as a tenured professor is to use this position not only to teach other, but to &lt;strong&gt;empower others&lt;/strong&gt;. Important to mention that this can only be done by the discipline of &lt;strong&gt;focusing on harder problems&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways in which we could &lt;strong&gt;empower others&lt;/strong&gt;. Students are our seeds, and they will grow longer and faster if we understand how to help them.
How about becoming closer to them? For instance, during teaching activities, how about running a retrospective (similar to those used in agile methods) once or twice? By providing a space for students to reflect on and discuss what worked well (and what did not), we all can improve. We would also be seen as someone available (professors are always busy).
When advising, we could think about spending more time with students. How about having lunch together? Or how about start bringing food to the weekly seminar? By making yourself available to discuss random thoughts with students, we could also understand what are their real needs and challenges. And it will be even more fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outreach activities are also very important to empower others. For instance, consider giving a talk to high school students once in a while. At their ages, many of them may be already thinking what career to follow. Moreover, it would be a terrific exercise for you to understand how to convince novice students that your research agenda is important. Similarly, consider also giving a talk to practitioners, and explain to them how your research could improve their work. If your work is not yet applied, consider extending your research agenda so that you could give a talk to practitioners by next year. There are many other outreach activities, such as teaching teenagers how to code or XXX. However, given the current lockdown situation, it may not be safe to run them now. Instead, how about doing a live about your work on youtube?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These activities may not help you in your next research paper. In fact, they would take a lot of time that you could devote to papers and grants. But this way you could potentially inspire someone (e.g., to pursue a career in research or to encourage other to use your research). Inspiring &amp;gt; publishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that by doing so, we may not have the same time or energy to pursue our research agenda on its fullest sense. My personal take here is: instead of trying to do any research work that I find interesting, I should try to understand what is the &lt;strong&gt;harder problem&lt;/strong&gt; I have at my table, and try my best to focus only on research works that could contribute to this big problem. As a consequence, by working more and more on one hard problem, it would become easier to talk about it, even for non-technical communities. It’s fair to mention that I still don’t know what is this big problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
***
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is easier said than done. In fact, it requires a lot of discipline to move from the writing-intense mode to the thinking-intense mode (e.g., thinking on how to distill this problem so that students could easily understand, thinking on how my work could improve practice, thinking on the hard and relevant research problems, etc). Moreover, this shift also has a shortcoming: since most of the work that I do is in collaboration with other researchers (then on several different subjects), by concentrating on one (or few) big problems, I also will have to say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; frequently.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">As of April the 4th, 2020, I am a tenured professor at UFPA, Brazil.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rethinking academic priorities during a pandemic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/rethinking-academic-priorities-during-a-pandemic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rethinking academic priorities during a pandemic" /><published>2020-03-27T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/rethinking-academic-priorities-during-a-pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/rethinking-academic-priorities-during-a-pandemic/">&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 outbreak is changing people work. Overnight, a good proportion of the global workforce had to go home and work remotely. Due to this not planned shift, I already perceived that it’s very hard to sustain to work at the usual pace during this pandemic, since, for instance, kids are at home, you may have many concerns about the future, etc. Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.org/blog/Its-OK-to-be-unproductive-during-COVID-19/&quot;&gt;it’s OK to be unproductive during this period&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take my personal case as an example. These days, I would say that I am working around 1/3 of what I am used to work. With two small kids (2yo and 4yo) at home, with the neverending house duties, and with a close relative with serious illness, I can hardly find some good quite hours to seat and work. As a consequence, the pile of work is nowhere near to be empty. It is really consuming to see this huge pile of work and not being able to get things done (even though I know that this is not particularly because of my laziness).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After thinking for a while, I come up with the obvious conclusion that I will not be able to finish this pile of work. Simple like that. Instead, I have to better prioritize what really needs to be done. The work that is not a priority right now will be on hold until I get to my normal schedule (if, by that time, that work is still any relevant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is, what is a priority in our pile of academic work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was that &lt;em&gt;everything is a priority&lt;/em&gt;. Well, if everything is a priority, and knowing that I’m not able to do everything that I want to do, then nothing is a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I term of research, I then realized that &lt;em&gt;only the work that would help students to graduate is a priority&lt;/em&gt;. Then, any work that does not have students is consequently not a priority at this moment. But still, I also interact with many students, from undergrads to PhDs, and they do differ a lot in terms of their needs. For instance, if I am involved in a work that is lead by a PhD student that wants to apply for academic jobs very soon, this would definitely be on my top priority. However, if a student wants to graduate soon, but does not intend to go for academic jobs, or perhaps the student already has a job (many PhD students in Brazil work part time during their PhDs), then this kind of work is also on my priority, but not as high as the student that wants to go for academic jobs. This is because one more publication could play a key role on the student assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I am rethinking my students’ the research agenda. During this time, I already mentioned to them that they are not require to work on full speed. On the contrary; they have to focus on their health, and on the health of their loved ones. If everything is fine, they could get back to work. But if they think they could provide some value on any work COVID-19-related (e.g., improving the visualization of COVID-19 cases in Brazil), they are also free to put their current research “on hold” and focus on any COVID-19-related work. Students looking for academic jobs very soon were not encouraged to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For teaching, my university suspended in person and online teaching activities, and we will get back only after this pandemic is done. So teaching is not a concern for me right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I am also chairing &lt;a href=&quot;http://cbsoft2020.imd.ufrn.br/sbcars.php&quot;&gt;a conference&lt;/a&gt;, and editing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sol.sbc.org.br/journals/index.php/jserd/&quot;&gt;journal&lt;/a&gt;. I see this kind of work as a priority. The reason is simple (and similar to the one I gave previously): some students finishing their degree need their papers published in order to increase their odds when applying for other positions. By doing these works, I would, indirectly, help others to improve their odds. The same is true for reviewing a paper. If I compromised to review, the review will be there by the time that we agreed. I can’t just say that I am not review the manuscript anymore. The negative impact on the reputation of the missing reviewer is not comparable to negative impact on the CV of the first author of the paper (often someone under time-bound contracts that needs that paper to be published more than anyone else). So reviews are also on priority. Any other kind of service and meetings are on hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my job as a professor is also to raise funding. Although funding is extremely important to help us pursue our research agenda, &lt;em&gt;I don’t see fundraising activities as a priority right now&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, I know. Funding is always important. But any grant that I may happen to apply these days, I would only receive the notification (luckily) by the end of the year, and, if accepted, I would only see any penny somewhere in 2021. By that time, this funding might not help any current student who is on the academic job market right now. Obviously, this eventual funding could help other students, but other students are not a priority at this moment. I recently also started &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.org/blog/Initial-thoughts-on-collaboration-with-the-industry/&quot;&gt;to collaborate with the industry&lt;/a&gt;. However, trying to establish an industry collaboration requires a ridiculous amount of time (in meetings, dealing with bureaucracies, etc). So, no. New industry collaborations are not a priority at this moment. However, it is obviously a priority to keep working on the already established collaborations (but the pace of work should also be discussed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, although it takes me about 1–2 hours to write down this blog post, I still see this as a priority. First, things became clear to me when I write here. Second, I may also help someone else who is struggling to balance work life academia, in particular during COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that new commitments are very likely to be declined (regardless of the subject, unfortunately). Apologies in advance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">How to cope with work during COVID-19</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s OK to be unproductive during COVID-19 outbreak</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Its-OK-to-be-unproductive-during-COVID-19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It's OK to be unproductive during COVID-19 outbreak" /><published>2020-03-21T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-03-21T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Its-OK-to-be-unproductive-during-COVID-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Its-OK-to-be-unproductive-during-COVID-19/">&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, the COVID-19 outbreak is starting to show its face in Brazil. However, due to the unpreparedness and the unprofessionalism of our president,
we may face one of the strongest impacts of COVID-19; perhaps even stronger than Italy or China. Our country is taking too much time to take real action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, when many Europe countries were already practicing social distancing, in Brazil, things were operating pretty much normal. Only this Thursday (March, 19th 2020) my university decided to suspend in person activities. It took a lot of time to make this decision. Many of us might be already infected, even if the public numbers are not yet popping up. Unfortunately, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Allen_Bartlett&quot;&gt;the greatest shortcoming of the human race is our inability to understand the exponential function&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overnight, many of us have to shift to online jobs. For those that a good part of the job is already done online, this shift may not have introduced a great burden. However, for a significant proportion of the workforce, although privileged to have the opportunity to keep working during this crisis, going full time online may introduce many challenges. Take my case as an example. As a professor, I have to teach, supervise, grade, fundraise, hire, give talks, write, review, etc. Obviously, many of these activities can be done (to a great extend) online. However, when going full time online I miss one key thing that perpetuates in most of these activities: &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, I can supervise online, but I have no idea if students are getting what I am saying. Yes, I can teach online, but I will never know if students are paying any attention to my recorded lecture. Yes, I can fundraise online, but I will not know if decision-makers are anyhow interested in my proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could say: “but you cannot be sure if a student is paying any attention even when interacting in person”. Yes, I cannot be sure, but I can have a gut feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I understand that going online introduces many limitations. I also understand that the point is not to replace the in person interaction to an online alternative. The goal is to alleviate the problem. We are going online only due to COVID-19. We (professors) may return to our traditional job schedule when it’s done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is: you may not be able to do your job in its fullest sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, you may have some loved ones that you should place additional care. You may have young kids struggling for your attention, now in full time mode, while you are juggling to keep your work done, now full time online. You may have aged relatives that may also be demanding your attention, even if, due to social distancing practices, you cannot visit them anymore; and you worry about them. You may have friends and colleagues around the world, facing unknown circumstances; and you worry about them. You may have students under difficult financial conditions; and you worry about them. Or you may be in a country lead by a sociopath; and you worry about everyone. Even if you don’t have any close relative in worrying conditions, you may still worry about everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all valid concerns, and I am sure there are many additional ones. Despite all of these, you still have to get things done at your now online job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is: you may not be able to do your job in its fullest sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of this crisis, you may see yourself cultivating an internal crisis: you are grateful for being able to work from home, but you are having a hard time to perform similarly as you performed when you worked from office. As a consequence, the COVID-19 outbreak could also place a toll on your research agenda. Perhaps you have to go to the lab to run experiments; Perhaps you have to submit an IRB to allow you to do your research; Perhaps you don’t have a quite place at home; Or perhaps you don’t have a chair at home. For those that are under time-bound contracts (like on a postdoc or on a tenure track), COVID-19 could also impact the likelihood to get a stable position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal take about this situation is: &lt;strong&gt;It’s OK to be unproductive during COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s OK to feel a bit lost. It’s OK to do not have much energy to work. Take your time, take care of those that need you the most, and (more importantly) take care of you. When you recover from all of this, you will get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you are in position of power, don’t be a jerk. You don’t need to be your students’ best friend to be supportive. Tell them that they don’t need to do their best work during the crisis. And keep your door (or Skype chat) always open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, if you are participating/will participate in a hiring committee, it is part of your job to pay attention to any potential candidate that had a decrease in their research outcomes during 2020/2021. Ask them why does this happen. Make sure you ask this in an welcoming manner to encourage the candidate to share her thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">Many other things matter</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Initial thoughts on collaboration with the industry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Initial-thoughts-on-collaboration-with-the-industry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Initial thoughts on collaboration with the industry" /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Initial-thoughts-on-collaboration-with-the-industry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Initial-thoughts-on-collaboration-with-the-industry/">&lt;p&gt;I another &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.org/blog/third-year-of-professoring/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote how hard 2019 was to me, in terms of my role as an academic in a place that does not seem to value much the work that I do. In this current scenario, it is becoming increasingly hard to keep working on our traditional research agenda, due to many reasons, including: lack of funding, lack of students interested in joining grad school, lack of recognition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, it is clear to me that, if I intend to keep working on my research agenda (to some extend at least), I have to find other ways to fund my work (and, consequently, my students). “Why not collaborating with the industry?”, they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seem many papers about academic-industrial collaborations, and I have also seen some colleagues in other universities doing very well because of these collaborations. Most intriguing, I have graduated in a university that is really known for collaborating a lot with big industry players. Sadly, I had no clue on how to start on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last few months, some colleagues and I have started to look for collaborations with industry patterns. I have been visiting many local companies, and talked with some decision-making people. Coming from an academic background, with very little industry-related research, it has been a challenge to me to understand their real needs and trying to find a way to get involved with them. In this blog post I try to summarize some of the lessons I learned thought out these months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the very beginning: how could I find decision-making people, who are always super busy, willing to talk about an eventual collaboration with this unknown professor? Here I had some luck because I happen to work in the same city that I grew up. So eventually, many old colleagues of mine are now playing decision-making roles. I updated my LinkedIn and started to look what my old peers were doing. For some of them, I sent a “hello, long time no see” message through the LinkedIn chat. I also sent some random messages (through LinkedIn and email) to other decision-making people (unknown to me), introducing me and asking for a meeting. I had some responses for the people that are already in my contact (not all of them), but I think I did not receive any response from those that are not on my contact list. This is clearly a problem for those that do not have any close contact with decision-making people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those that answered my message, I did not have much problem scheduling a meeting. But in this point, I started to wonder what I would propose to them? Just asking for money to do research does not sound a good strategy. I knew I had to propose something concrete to them. I then started to search for what kind of work do their companies do, what are their clients, etc. Since software engineering is my research area, and knowing that the company does a lot of, say, mobile development, I could perhaps argue that we could improve productivity or time to market by using strategies x, y, or z. However, although I still think that it is a good approach to look for their clients to see what do they do, it is a kind of unconvincing for me, as an academic, to suggest to technical people that they should do/use other technical stuff. I perhaps could indeed help them, but suggesting this in the very first meeting, when none of them knows me, sounds a bit arrogant at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, we proposed something called &lt;a href=&quot;http://gustavopinto.org/lost+found/ease2018.pdf&quot;&gt;Rapid Reviews&lt;/a&gt;, in which a researcher goes to a company, talks to representative people, and tries to grasp what are the problems they are facing (and eventually come up with an evidence-based solution to them). I thought a lot about doing a rapid review within these companies. But I also found a bit awkward to go to a meeting without any clear problem to discuss, and, in the meeting, propose to a research-like work, to only after that have something concrete to say. Decision-making people may be just too busy to hear about rapid reviews, I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Brazil we also have this “Informatic Law” in which companies could destinate part of their taxes to invest in R&amp;amp;D. Unfortunately, this law is not yet crystal clear to me, and I found strange to propose something that I do not fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my decision was to go to the meetings pretty much to introduce myself, meet representative people, try to grasp their problems, and go home to think about how I could help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found two interesting things in this process: first, when someone invite you for a meeting, they do want you there. These are very busy people, and they would not waste their time with you if you could not provide any valuable asset for them. Second, and perhaps most surprisingly, some decision-making people are eager to collaborate with academics. I heard from two business patterns that they already searched for collaborations within the university by themselves, but did not have any response. One of them also told me that he wants to do a donation to the university because he did not find a way to collaborate with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes the meetings were not that easy. Once a representative member receive me, asked me to take a seat, and then asked: &lt;strong&gt;how could I help you?&lt;/strong&gt;. I was not expecting that question right upfront, and it really intimidated me. I did not have any straightforward answer to this question, so I may have said a lot of nonsense. In the end I said that I was looking for a way to fund students. He then said that his company is having a hard time trying to hire good people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a good sign for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this guy is having a hard time trying to hire people, other companies are also having the same problem. The problem is not only salary. This is cultural. I live in a city in the heart of Amazon, the rain forest, very far from the big cities (São Paulo or Rio de Janeiro). Many employees leave because they look for other challenges in other places/countries. These people are having a hard time to find new skilled employees. Where are these people?  ….. Obviously, in the university! I am a professor. I have many, many students every year. These students want to work for companies. Bingo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I have this realization, I finally have a way to approach decision-making people in our local software companies. &lt;strong&gt;I know that you are having a hard time to hire good developers. You know what, if you could offload one small, non-risky project to the university, I could supervise some students that would work with the same methods and technology that you use in your company. After 1–2 years, these students would be ready to join your company.&lt;/strong&gt; I remember one business man saying that this “sounds like music to me”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding was good to keep the door open for collaborations, but I soon realized that this was not enough to “sign a paper”. Another common problem that I realized is that many of these companies are having problems to use/integrate different software systems. So then “integrating systems/databases” also became a recurring topic in the meetings. This integration process naturally evolved to data mining and analytics. And here we finally arrived in the research arena. Although python+pandas are readily available and pretty easy to use, somehow decision-making people believes that academics are best ones to do this job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many months trying to establish collaborations with industry patterns, perhaps the most important lesson learned to me is that, before finding the problem to work together, you should find a reason to “keep the door open”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gustavo Pinto</name><email>gpinto@ufpa.br</email></author><summary type="html">How to start?</summary></entry></feed>